It will take one second.
>> All right. Hi everyone. Welcome. Thanks
for joining us. My name is Robert. I'll
be your MC. We're joined with the
fabulous and well- read and super
knowledgeable Deerra O. Sullivan. She's
going to talk about the Pentagon 911
memorial. So, Dearra, take it away.
>> Good evening everyone. My name is Dearro
Sullivan and I am a bit of a history
buff. And when I found this group, I was
so excited because here was a bunch of
people who loved history the same way
that I did. So, I always appreciate
Robert allowing me to do things like
this. And today, we're going to
concentrate on 911. And not only we're
going to concentrate on 911, but we're
going to talk about 911 at the Pentagon.
I don't think that story is as well
known as what happened in New York or
Shanksville, Pennsylvania. So, we're
just going to concentrate on what
happened on September 11th um at the
Pentagon. So, we're going to start with
a quote from President George W. Bush,
which is one of the worst days in
American history. Saw some of the
bravest acts in American's history. We
will always honor the heroes of 9/11 and
here in at this hollowed place we pledge
that we will never forget their
sacrifice. So George W. Bush dedicated
the 911 memorial at the Pentagon in 2008
and that is a quote from him.
So let's go to the next slide. So what
we're going to do is we're going to do a
timeline of what happened just to remind
everybody of what happened on 911. So
we're going to start at 7:59 in the
morning. American Airlines Flight 11
departs Boston bound for Los Angeles. At
8:14, United Flight 175, departs Boston,
bound for Los Angeles. 8:19, Betty
Young, who is a flight attendant on
American Airlines flight 11, calls the
American Airlines Reservation Center to
advise them of a hijacking. 8:20,
American Airlines flight 77, departs
Washington Dallas for Los Angeles. 8:24
air traffic control records a statement
from the n from the flight 11 hijacker
stating quote we have some planes just
stay quiet and you'll be okay we are
returning to the airport
8:37 FAA notifies NORAD of a suspected
hijacking in response two fighter planes
are scrambled out of Massachusetts they
will head out to sea that was part of
their training 824 United flight 93
departs Newark bound for San Francisco
it was scheduled to depart at 8:00 a.m.
8:46 American Airlines 11 crashes into
the north tower of the World Trade
Center around the 93rd floor. The fire
chief battalion the fired battalion
chief Joseph Feifer makes the first
radio message announcing quote we just
had a plane crash into the upper floor
of the World Trade Center, transmit a
second alarm fire and start relocating
companies into the area.
903 United Flight 175 crashes into the
south tower of the World Trade Center at
590 mph around the 78th floor. The NY
I'm sorry, FDNY calls for a level four
mobilization. Almost 2,000 firefighters
will respond. 905. The White House Chief
of Staff Andy Card interrupts President
George W. Bush while he's listening to a
reading lesson at an elementary school
in Sarasota, Florida, stating, quote, "A
second plane hit the second tower.
America's under attack."
9008 FAA grounds all take off from New
York City airports. 911, the last of the
path train, that's the train that goes
underneath the World Trade Center,
leaves the World Trade Center. The
station will be vacant when the towers
eventually collapse. 8:21. All bridges,
bridges, and tunnels into Manhattan are
now closed.
928 FAA notifies NORAD of a suspected
hijacking of Flight American Flight 77
after passengers notify family members
on the ground. 937 American Airlines
Flight 77 crashes into the western
facade of the Pentagon at 530 mph.
924 942 For the first time in US
history, FAA grounds all takeoffs and
all flights are to land immediately.
Over the next two and a half hours, some
3,300 commercial flights and 1,200
private planes will land safely in
either the US or Canada. 9:45 The White
House and the US capital are evacuated.
Women are told to kick off their heels
and quote, "Run for their lives." In the
White House situation room, a dead list
is sent to the CIA operation center. So,
this is basically the list of staff who
were remaining in the situation room
when they think a plane is inbound.
1057 passengers revolt on flight 93 to
try to recontra control of the cockpit
from the hijackers.
959 the south tower of the World Trade
Center collapses. 959 For the first time
in US history, a continuity of
government procedures are implemented.
The heads or deputies of all federal
agencies must leave Washington for an
alternate location. 10:00 a.m. Battalion
Chief Joseph Feifer from the North Tower
orders all firefighters to evacuate the
towers. 10:02 The Sears Tower in Chicago
is being evacuated. 10:03 United Flight
93 crashes in a field in Shanksville,
Pennsylvania. The crash site was
approximately 20 minutes flying time to
Washington DC. 10:10 The E-ring roof at
the Pentagon collapses. 10:15 NORAD
operations centers in Colorado closes
its blast door. Cheyenne Mountain, which
is headquarters to NORAD, is designed to
survive a nuclear attack. 9:29, the
North Tower of the World Trade Center
collapses along with the Marriott Hotel,
which is located at its base. 1053
Defense Secretary Donald Rumsfelds
orders all military to be placed on
DEFCON 3, which is the highest level uh
since the AF since the ArabIsraeli war
of 1993. It's 1973. So DEFCON 3 is
basically DEFCON 1 is nuclear war. At
11:02, the New York City mayor Rudy
Giuliani calls for the evacuation of
lower Manhattan south of Canal Street.
This will impact 1 million people. 10 10
I'm sorry 12:16 the US airspace over the
continental United States is clear of
all commercial and private aviation 1:00
President Bush makes a statement from
Barksdale Air Force Base in Louisiana
placing all US military on a high alert
before the statement is released Air
Force One is released sent back into the
air 239
New York City Mayor Giuliani is asked to
estimate the number of casualties at the
World Trade Center. He replies, quote,
"More than any of us can bear." 2:50,
President Bush arrives at Offet Air
Force Base in Nebraska for a national
security conference teleconference.
At 4:35,
4:36, President Bush departs Offet Air
Force Base on Air Force One bound for
Washington after being told that all
aircraft are now accounted for.
520, the seven World Trade Center
collapses. More than 100 private and
public vessels, naval vessels, evacuate
350 to 500,000 people from lower
Manhattan in about 8 hours. For some
historical context, it took 8 days to
evacuate that many soldiers from Dunkerk
during World War II.
654, President Bush returns to the White
House. At 8:30, President Bush addresses
the nation from the Oval Office.
So 200 2,96
people were killed on September 11th due
to the terrorist attacks. 265 were
killed on four planes. 2,606
were killed in the World Trade Center.
343 were New York City firemen. 72 were
law enforcement. More than 90% of those
who died were about were at or above the
impact zone of the planes. So, the first
plane hit the north tower above the 93rd
floor or at the 93rd floor. We are not
aware of anyone getting out who was
above the 93rd floor. The second plane
came in um less than about 10 minutes
later and it hit the 78th floor, but it
came in at an angle. I don't know if
anyone remembers that, but as a result,
there was one staircase that actually
survived. A handful of people managed to
make their way from the 78th above the
impact zone, made their way out, and
finally got out of the tower alive, but
it was just a handful. There was a lot
of confusion, and people didn't realize
that there was an emergency staircase
that was still in operation.
Between 100 and 200 people jumped or
fell from the World Trade Center, one of
the most interesting things is the human
element to that. So, you had women who
were jumping from the World Trade
Center, but as they did so, they held
their skirts down. So they didn't
Amazing what people do. There were 1,653
victims who have been positively
identified. The fires burned in the
World Trade Center until December 2001.
125 were killed inside the Pentagon. 55
were military personnel. 33 were US
Navy. 22 were US Army. Lieutenant
General Timothy Ma who is the army
deputy chief of staff was the highest
ranking military officer killed at the
Pentagon. Also killed was retired US
rear US Navy rear admiral Wilson flag.
He just happened to be on flight 77.
According to the 911 commission to plan
and conduct their attack the 911 plotter
spent between $400 and $500,000.
So they did this whole thing for under a
half a million dollars.
Within weeks, President Bush will
request $20 billion in supplemental
funds from Congress to cover the costs
associated with the tax. So, this is not
the military. This is just to deal with
the attacks with the understanding that
they would come back for an additional
request for funds in February 20 of
2002.
So, we're going to focus on kind of as
we create the timeline. So, we're going
to start with the Pentagon being built.
We're going to talk about the World
Trade Center. We're going to talk about
the reconstruction of the Pentagon, how
that started in earnest in 1994.
We're going to talk about the Oklahoma
City bombing. And then finally, we're
going to talk about what happened at the
Pentagon.
So, let's start with this. Who can tell
me who this gentleman is? Anyone
know who this gentleman is in the Oh,
wow. That was fast. Okay, let's talk
about Leslie Groves.
So, Leslie Groves was born in August of
1896. He was the son of a US Army
chaplain and graduated fourth in his
class at West Point in 1918. In August
of 1991, sorry, August 1941, he was
appointed to manage the construction
project for what is now known as the
Pentagon. In September of 1942, he was
appointed to a new project. He was going
to be the military supervisor for the
quote Manhattan project. He died in 1970
in Washington DC, and he's buried at
Arlington Cemetery, and this is his
grave. He recalled later that he was
hoping he would get into the war theater
so he could find a little piece. So,
anyone know what date they broke ground
on the Pentagon? It's kind of an obscure
thing.
So, they broke ground to build the
Pentagon. Anyone know what date it was?
Yeah. September 11th, 1941.
which the irony of that um we are not
aware that this was the date that they
chose uh had anything to do with the
building of the Pentagon. It just wasn't
a date that was was done with no
fanfare, no bands, no nothing. Literally
they just started digging. Um they just
tried to put it up as quickly as
possible. So let's talk about the
building of the Pentagon.
So the architect was a gentleman by the
name of George Burstrom. He was given
three days to come up with a design that
could accommodate 40,000 employees and
10,000 cars. Now, that always fascinates
me. I don't know how all these people
are going to fit in 40,000 people are
fitting in 10,000 cars, but we'll leave
that alone. He had multiple parameters,
including the original site had five
roads that surrounded it, and there was
a severe steel shortage leading up to
the war. So, the building could only be
five stories. So, originally, the
original site was scrapped and it ended
up being the what they chose instead was
where Hoover Field was. So after uh
World War I, if you wanted to fly in and
out of Washington DC, you flew to Hoover
Field, which is located where the
Pentagon is today. So Roosevelt
personally chose Hoover Field. And in
the 1960s, even more interesting, if you
go back, this land was originally owned
by Robert E. Lee's family. So Robert E.
Lee, who was the Confederate general, he
married into the Custous family. His
wife was a Custous. Who are the Custous?
Well, that's uh Martha Custous
Washington. So Martha Custous was a
widow when she married George Washington
and had two children. The Custous family
owned a lot of the land of what is now
Arlington and some of that land was
where the Pentagon is today. We could do
a whole presentation on George
Washington and the I'm sorry on Roberty
Lee and his family and Arlington. Um,
however, Roosevelt saw the design and
really liked it. And one of the reasons
he liked the design is because it
reminded him of Civil War forts. So, I
actually sat through a presentation
quite recently about all of the forts.
So, every major road that came into
Washington DC had a fort built on it.
And the idea was is to not allow a
Confederate army obviously to infiltrate
Washington DC, which was the capital of
the of the Union at the time.
it has been. So they built all these
forts and most of them had five sides.
So when the president saw this, he
really liked the design and so that
became the design of the Pentagon.
Now there was an issue with the
bathrooms. Anyone know what the
controversy is with the bathrooms at the
Pentagon? Seems like an odd thing to
say.
Anyone remember anything about why there
was an issue with the bathrooms at the
Pentagon?
Bingo. Black and white. So let's talk
about that. The Pentagon planners found
it necessary to design the building with
separate facilities for both white and
colored. So twice the number of
bathrooms were created for the
anticipated staff levels. However, in
June of 1941, President Roosevelt issues
executive order 8802 which prohibited
segregation in federal um among federal
employees. Virginia was not happy about
this and in fact a letter was sent by
the governor of Virginia to um the
president at the time. president's like,
"Yeah, I got a war to win. We'll deal
with this later." So, even from its
opening, all facilities have been open
to both black and white employees,
making the Pentagon the first
non-segregated building in all of
Virginia.
Now, in theory, it is possible to get
from the furthest point of the Pentagon
to the other end of the Pentagon. So, in
other words, you can walk from one end
of the Pentagon through the courtyard to
the other end of the Pentagon in 10
minutes. My assumption is you would be
moving very fast, but yes, apparently it
is possible.
So, I don't know if anyone remembers the
1990 1990 1991 Persian Gulf War, but I
am old enough to remember it. Um, I
remember CNN. I remember very modern
war. I remember pictures of bridges
getting bombed and of guided missiles
and airplanes and satellite imaging and
all of this was being done out of a
building that leaked every time it
rained.
So when the Pentagon was built in 1941,
1942, they threw that thing up. They put
it up you they worked seven days a week.
It was under war conditions. They put
that building up as quickly as possible
and they put it up with the least amount
of steel that they could. So the time
was they kept on saying that you know we
saved enough steel to build a
battleship.
So there are no there was like one
elevator in the entire building. There
were a lot of ramps and there are very
few stairs because again stairs required
steel and so it's just not it was built
very very quickly. It was built well,
but it was thrown up. And so by 1992,
1993, it was painfully evident that the
Pentagon building was showing its age.
So a trial balloon was actually floated
to tear down the Pentagon and start all
over. It would actually be cheaper to do
that. And not only was the building
having problems, but that just wasn't
have the capable, you know, the
technology that was available. I think
when the Pentagon was built, there was
one telephone for every four people.
Well, by 1992, you've got telephones,
you've got now internet or the
beginnings of it anyway. And then you've
got fax machines and you have secure
mach there's just there's not enough.
The technology is too old and most there
are wires that go everywhere and most
people don't even know where they go.
So, they have to spend a lot of time and
energy just trying to figure out get it
technologically more advanced.
So again, there's this idea we're going
to tear it down and we're going to start
over. Instead, Congress declares it a
national landmark. Now, it has been
declared a national landmark. There is
the idea of tearing it down and starting
over is dead. So, our only we have to
leave it basically as it looks. So, we
can renovate the inside, but the
exterior has to stay the same and the
guts of the building basically or the
physical structure of the building has
to stay the same. So in 1994 they begin
their plans for reconstruction.
Now what's also going on in this period
in the '9s with the military? Anyone
remember far back that far back?
So the the military was going through
big changes in the early 90s after the
end of the Bush uh presidency and the
beginning of the Clinton presidency. And
one of those was a base realignment. So
there was really a draw down of the
military following um the Persian Gulf
War. And so you had bases closing all
across the country. And at the same
time, the Pentagon keeps on going back
to Congress saying, you know, we need
more money to to to revitalize the
Pentagon. And they're like, great, but
you just closed down a base in my
district. So nobody was that anxious to
give them the money to do that
considering that there was already this
draw down going on with the military. So
there's this tug and pull going on.
But by 1998
this is finally g gathering steam and
it's moving ahead. So let's talk about
some of the events that occurred
terrorist events that occurred pre 911
which kind of led up to what we call the
plains plan.
So 1931 was the first time terrorists
hijacked a plane. Like well it was like
20 years after planes first were
developed and somebody decided oh let's
go ahead and let's grab one. And of
course the problem with grabbing an
aircraft is nobody can fly it. So it it
basically it was surrounded by
revolutionaries upon landing. It was a
panam flight male carrier and eventually
they were released because there wasn't
any they couldn't do anything with it.
But in 199 1970 was a new wave of
terrorism that occurred using aircraft
and the first one was September of 1970
when terrorists terrorist hijacked four
planes in one day. Uh two were
successful. Eventually the hostages are
going to be released and their jailed
comrades are also going to be released.
1993 terror strike again. This time
destroying an aircraft using incendiary
grenades. They hijack a second plane,
fly all over the Mediterranean, end up
in Greece where 34 hostages are killed.
Another one was in 1984, this time TWWA
flight 847. Two hijackers forced a pilot
to fly to multiple locations, killed a
US Navy diver, and then a hostages were
held for weeks in Lebanon until finally
they were released. So, what was the
most, if you were know anything about
aviation, and I don't know how many of
you do, but I do because I work for TSA,
but what would be the most important
terrorism event involving aviation prior
to the events of 9/11? Anyone want to
hazard a guess?
So there's well I think I have it listed
here. Lockerby Scotland. So let's talk
about that. In December of 1988,
Panaman Flight 103 explodes over
Lockerby Scotland due to explosives in
check baggage. 259 people are killed in
the air and then 11 on the ground.
Eventually the country of Libya takes
responsibility.
And this is a really big deal for
aviation. And the reason for that is at
the time in 1998, no technology exists
that can screen check baggage for
explosives in any quick period of time.
You're talking about opening each bag.
And that's just not practical when
you're looking at how many people fly a
year. So as a result of Panaman Flight
103, FAA starts putting huge amounts of
money into the ether to try to get
companies to develop new explosive
detection equipment. So it is a result
of Pan Amflight 103 that we now have the
explosive detection equipment. So when
you check in your bag and sometimes at
airports you see these big things that
look like the size of minivans and your
bags go in them. Those are explosive
detection equipment and that was
developed because of pan flight 103. It
was slowly being deployed in the uh
months before 911. But it really was
after 9/11 that this technology which
now existed could be deployed in huge
numbers following the events of 911.
So who is this individual?
Anyone know who he is?
Excuse me.
No. Somebody said bes No, he's not
Richard Reid. So this is basically pre
911.
Oh yes, we are recording this. Sorry,
I'm just looking at some of the
comments. Um, this person is a gentleman
by the name of Ramsay Yousef. So, let's
talk about who Ramsay Yousef is. So,
Ramsay Yousef was born in Kuwait to
parents from Pakistan in 1968. He
graduated from Swansea Institute in the
UK with a degree in electrical
engineering. He is important because he
created the car bomb for the first
attack on the World Trade Center in
February of 1993.
Six people were killed. More than a
thousand people were injured. Most of
the people who were injured were injured
as a result of the evacuation. People
tripped and fell. People had heart
attacks, asthma attacks because of all
the smoke um that was going on in the
building. He is actually going to leave
the country pretty soon after the
attack. And so he will not be um charged
immediately following this. So what his
plan was is here are the two buildings.
This is kind of rough, but go along with
me here. So his plan was to put the bomb
here basically at the base of the
building. And the idea was is that it
would start to collapse, go into this
one, and then both of them would go
down. Um instead, the building held and
it did blow a hole in it, but it did
hold. And as a result of that, uh six
people died who were in the parking
garage. uh but most of the people who
were injured were injured as a result of
the evacuation. Now he is going to flee
the country and in 1994 he is going to
be in the Philippines.
Now if you Google the word the panka
plot you're going to be like oh yeah
I've heard of this. Isn't this the plot
to assassinate uh President Clinton when
he's in the Philippines? Yes. Isn't the
Panka plot the plot to run a plane into
the into the CIA headquarters? Yes.
Isn't the Panka plot have something to
do with liquid bombs? Yes. All of that
falls under the heading of the Pena
Plot, which were ideas being put
together by Ramsay Yousef. So, in the
fall of 1994, Ramsay Yousef is now in
the Philippines. He actually has an
apartment very close to the Embassy of
the Holy Sea, which is the papal the
Catholic Church. And he is now
developing the Panka plot. and we're
going to focus in on his plan to put 11
bombs on board aircraft from the Far
East heading to the United States. So on
December 11th, 1994, he is going to
board a flight from Manila to Japan.
He's going to get off the flight on a
planned over overlay and then he's going
to leave the bomb on board the aircraft.
The bomb is going to explode. A
passenger will be killed, but the plane
will land safely. So in January of 1945,
his plan is to place 11 of these bombs
because now he figured I can get him
past aviation security. All he needs to
do is make him a little bit bigger and
he can take down the plane. Now he is
going to be thwarted from his plan when
his apartment catches on fire. So he's
got his apartment. He's got all these
chemicals lying around. A fire breaks
out in his apartment. He's there with
his roommate. They try to put it out.
They can't. They leave the apartment.
Fire department arrives. Um, they see
all this chemicals and all these things
lying around. The police are there. Uh,
they start talking to the neighbors.
They're talking about these individuals
who live in this apartment who are a
little odd. They bring in the police.
They get a search warrant. And then they
find these computers with all this
information on it. It is in Arabic. They
don't understand it. They bring in the
American FBI and the FBI translate and
goes, "Oh shit." Um, so as a result of
this, he's actually thwarted. So he
doesn't manage to put the 11 bombs on
board the aircraft. He again is going to
escape. So as soon as his apartment
catches on fire, he is going to end up
going to the airport and he's going to
fly back to Pakistan. But his roommate
will get caught and he is going to be
arrested and questioned by officials in
the Philippines. So now they're going to
have a really good idea as to what his
plan was, how he intended to do it, and
who were his conspirators. But he is
going to escape. He will end up in
Pakistan and then about a month or two
later he is actually going to be he is
going to be betrayed by some of his
associates because there's a huge bounty
for him and he will be turned over to
Pakistan for authorities and eventually
be turned over to American authorities.
He is currently located in a supermax
prison in Florence, Colorado. Now this
supermax prison is kind of interesting.
Does anyone know any other famous people
he may have spent time with in a
supermax prison in Florence, Colorado? I
don't know about El Chapo. I have to
look that up. That's a good thought. I
was actually thinking of two other
people. Oh, so you so yeah,
Leo. No, the Uni Bomber. Correct. So
actually the uni bomber spent some time
they were on the same wing and uh
according to published reports the uni
bomber and Ramsay youfs used to have
conversations. I don't know friends is
the right word or maybe more that they
just happen to be in the same spot at
the same time. There are very few people
to talk to but apparently the two of
them in prison not before prison but as
prisonmates um did talk to each other on
fairly uh recent basis. No, actually the
Oklahoma City, we're going to talk about
him. Um, but there's another gentleman.
He was very famous here in Washington DC
and he had nothing to do with terrorism,
but he was considered a traitor to the
United States. And he's correct. So,
Robert Henen actually is also in the
same wing in the supermax prison as
Ramsay Yousef. Apparently, according to
published reports, they don't chat a
whole lot. So, Robert Henson really
doesn't want to have much to do with
Ramsay Yousef. Or it could be the
opposite. Either way, they're not
buddies.
So, let's talk about this gentleman. Who
can tell me who he is?
Khaled Shik Muhammad. Correct. Let's
talk about Khaled Shik Muhammad. And why
is Khaled Shik Muhammad so important?
Well, for our benefit, the interesting
thing about Khaled Shik Muhammad is he
is Ramsay Yousef's uncle.
So, he actually spent time in the
Philippines working on the Pachanka
plot.
So, Rams KSM, so they refer to him as
the military. He was born in either 1964
or 1965 in Pakistan. He graduated from
the North Carolina Agricultural and
Technical State University with a degree
in mechanical engineering in 1986.
So he is considered the architect of the
911 um attack. So he's the one who came
up with the plan and what he referred to
it as the plains plan. So he is going to
spend time in 1994, 1993 and 1994 in the
Philippines with Ramsay Yousef
and he is going to take some of the
ideas that Ramsay Yousef has come up
with for the Panka plot and he's going
to come up with a new plan and that plan
is going to be known as the plains plan
and you're going to understand how he
came up with it. So the first thing he's
going to do is he's going to take some
of the plans that Ramsay has come up
with. The first one is World Trade
Center.
That's a good idea. Let's see if we can
figure out how to take down the World
Trade Center. Aircraft.
Yeah, let's try that again. Let's figure
out how to use aircraft. Third,
explosives. Way too complicated. Your
chances of getting caught go up
considerably if you start thinking about
using explosives. So, okay. So, this is
how he comes up with the plan. And it's
painfully obvious how he did it. So,
World Trade Center, good target using
aircraft. Good idea. Don't use
explosives.
It's the pieces are all there. So, it is
from this he is going to come up with
the plain's plan and the plain's plan is
going to be then presented to um Osama
bin Laden and Osama bin Laden is going
to give him the money. So, as a result
of this, we have 911.
Now, uh, KSM is going to be arrested in
March of 2003. He's going to be captured
in Pakistan and he is turned over to US
authorities.
So, not all terrorists come from
overseas. Who remembers this incident?
What is this from?
Anyone recognize this picture? It might
take a few seconds for sometimes the
Yes, correct. Oklahoma City. So, let's
talk about Oklahoma City.
Timothy McVey, who was an Army vet, and
his accomplished Terry Nichols, filled a
rider rented truck with 7,000 pounds of
explosives. At 8:57 a.m., he parked the
car, parked the truck bomb in front of
the Merurl Federal Building in Oklahoma
City, lit a fuse, and exited the
vehicle. At 9:02, the truck bomb
exploded, shearing off onethird of the
building. Now, why do I bring this up?
Because this event really started
changing national security planners. So,
for example, the um Pennsylvania Avenue
in front of the White House was closed
and it's now closed permanently. In
addition, in 1994,
the Pentagon reconstruction project had
started. And it really started with the
idea, we're going to renovate the, you
know, we're going to make sure it stops
leaking every time it rains. In addition
to that, we're going to figure out how
to do some of the wires and some of the
technical changes involved with making
the building more modern.
But now we're going to start figuring
out, okay, well, let's see if we can add
some security features. We're doing it
anyway. We're having to vitalize the
building. Let's see if we can add some
security measures on top of what is
already there. And the idea is these
security measures are going to quote
minimize the damage caused by a truck
bomb of this size.
So let's talk about Osama bin Laden. So
Osama bin Laden was born in 1997 into
one of Saudi Arabia's wealthiest
families. His father was an immigrant
from South Yemen. He built a small
construction business into a
multibillion dollar company when he was
contracted by the Saudi royal family to
build hotels and other accommodations in
the holy city of Mecca. When his father
died in 1968, Bin Laden inherited an
estimated $30 billion and that was in
1938. That's a lot of money in 1938.
Al-Qaeda, which is known as the base or
loosely translated into the base,
originates back in 1997 when the Soviet
Union invaded Afghanistan. At some
point, Osama bin Laden is going to
travel to Afghanistan to join the fight.
And more importantly, he's going to
bring his money with him. So, he will
become a leader of al-Qaeda because of
his money. In 1996, bin Laden issues a
fatwa or call for holy war for the US
military to leave Saudi Arabia following
the Persian Gulf War. Osama bin Laden
issues a second fatwa in 1998 together
with alsi
saying that wrong, declares war against
the United States. He stated, quote, "We
do not have to differentiate between
military or civilian. as far as we
concerned, they the Americans are all
targets."
In his December 1999 interview, Bin
Laden related his reiterated his
ideology and objected to US military
presence in Saudi Arabia. He proclaimed
that the US was too near Mecca, which
provided a provocation to the entire
Muslim world.
Now, he's also an interesting character.
In 1991 when um 1990 when uh Iraq
invaded um invocated um
Kuwait um he actually went to a
representative of the royal family and
offered to bring his soldiers from
al-Qaeda to defend um Saudi Arabia which
is of course the holy land. and instead
the Saudi royal family got a better
offer which of course was from the US
military who offered to provide 500,000
members of the military to defend Saudi
Arabia. So they took that offer and kind
of um did not take the offer from Osama
bin Laden. So that is also an
interesting tidbit.
So let's talk about now Osama bin Laden
will be killed on May 2nd 2011. He's
killed by US Navy Seals in Pakistan and
he is buried at sea. So let's talk about
these two bombings in US embassies in
Africa. So on August 7th, 1998,
224 people, including 12 Americans, are
killed and another 4,500 are injured
when two truck bombs explode at US
embassies in Kenya and Tanzania. Many of
the injuries are caused by flying
debris, including glass. That's
important. That will be important later.
Eventually, the FBI will link the
bombers who are members of the Egyptian
um
uh jihad, who is linked to both Osama
bin Laden and al-Qaeda.
19 they the FBI adds Osama bin Laden to
the list of the 100 most wanted. In on
August 20th, President Bill Clinton
orders cruise missiles launched on bin
Laden's training sites in Afghanistan
and against a pharmaceutical plant in
Sudan. In November of 1998, the United
States indictes both bin Laden and 21
unders, charging them with the bombing
of the two US embassies and conspiring
to commit other acts of terrorism.
Don't think they were that impressed to
be indicted in a US court, but that's
just me. So, now we are going to move
ahead and we're going to talk about PEN
ren. People like, what's pen? Well, it's
the military. We have to have a a um an
acronym for everything. So the
renovation of the Pentagon begins on and
at least on paper in 1998 and they
finally get the money oh sorry it begins
in 1994 they finally get the money and
begin it in earnest in 1998.
So let's talk about that.
So following the terrorist attacks in
1998 and the US embassy attacks in 19
1995 and 1998, the decision is made to
add additional security measures to the
Pentagon to minimize the damage from a
truck bomb.
So let's talk about these new security
measures that are going to be put in at
the Pentagon. The first thing they're
going to do is they're going to add
steel to the exterior ring. So you have,
if you ever look at the Pentagon, they
have this um limestone kind of on the
exterior. Right behind the limestone is
brick. And when they went and they took
some of the brick out, they're like,
"Wow, they really threw this building up
because it wasn't very even. They threw
the building up and they were working at
night and perhaps they could have."
Anyway, so what they did is they
replaced that brick with steel. So steel
beams were put in on the exterior ring.
And again, the idea is to better
withstand a blast from a truck bomb. The
other thing that they added was blast
resistant windows. So remember, we
talked about how many people were
injured because when the bomb went off
in the embassy, you had flying debris,
including glass. So what we're going to
do is we're going to make that glass on
the exterior ring much more blast
resistant to pro to lessen injuries.
We're also going to add cavlar. So the
cavlar is what you basically wear as far
as a bulletproof vest. So, what we're
going to do is we're going to put some
of that cavlar actually inside the
interior of the building. And the idea
is to basically hold on some of that
debris so it doesn't go flying.
So, to prevent um flying debris or to at
least lessen flying debris. The other
thing they're going to put in is fire
sprinklers. This technology did not
exist in 1990 uh 1992 when they built
the building. So, for 50 years, the
Pentagon didn't have fire sprinklers. So
they're going to add that as one of the
security features they're going to put
in uh following 1998. So the plan is is
we're going to do it by wedge. So we're
going to take one wedge and everybody
who works in that wedge is going to go
over and work in Pentagon City or
Crystal City. And they're all like
bye-bye. Um because Crystal City has
gyms and they've got um nice facilities
and elevators so and they've got you
know climate control. The Pentagon not
so much. So they're all fine with moving
into um Pentagon City. They're working
from there. So that particular area of
the building will be completely empty
while they go in and they do the
renovations. So they're going to start
on the western facade near where the
helport is. So on any given day,
approximately 23,000 people work at the
Pentagon.
So now we're going to focus in on what
happened on September 11th at the
Pentagon.
So, at 8:20 a.m., American Airlines
Flight 77 departs Washington Dallas
bound for Los Angeles. Between 8:51 and
8:47, Flight 77 was hijacked. At 8:46,
the at flight 77's transponder is turned
off. At this point, it basically
disappears completely off of FAA's
radars. They have no idea where it went.
9:16 Barbara Olsen calls her husband
Theodore Olsen, who is the US solicitor
general, to advise her that her flight
has been hijacked. Theodore Olsen is
like the number two person at the
Justice Department here in the United
States. Olsen attempts to contact his
boss, who is the US Attorney General,
but is unsuccessful prior to the plane
crash. So, a lot of the information we
have about what happened on Flight 77
comes from that conversation that
Barbara Olsen had. She says the two
pilots have been removed from the
cockpit and that's kind of one of the
only things that we know about what
happened on board that aircraft. At 9:32
FAA air traffic controllers at Dulles
airport notify Reagan airport that
anodak aircraft is heading towards them
at huge speed. At 9:37, Flight 77
crashes in the first floor of the
Pentagon at four 530 mph with 59
passengers on board and 36,000 lbs of
jet fuel. The plane was traveling so low
that they hit light posts along the way.
After 9/11, the FAA had various pilots
and simulators attempt to follow the
hijacker's flight plan into the
Pentagon. Most pilots flew their planes
into the ground. So you have the plane
goes west heading towards Pennsylvania.
At some point it's hijacked and starts
making it way back to Washington. So it
basically makes its way back to Dallasos
airport and then it is flying towards
DC. Once it finds DC, it sees the
Pentagon. You can tell what it is from
the air. So now they're going to do this
corkcrew maneuver to lose altitude. So
they're flying fairly low for a
commercial aircraft, but they're still
too high just to go straight down. So,
they're going to do this circular
motion, this corkcrew, and they're going
to come down and around until eventually
they get low enough where they can start
heading into the Pentagon. Now, based on
this flight plan, the FAA had all these
pilots try to do this. And most of them,
just because of the how fast and what
steep they were going, they just went
right into the ground. But somehow, the
911 hijacker was able to pull up just
enough to go right into the first floor
of the Pentagon.
So now we're going to talk about some of
the stories of heroes and survivors.
So the first person we're going to talk
about is Father Stefan McGra. He was a
Catholic priest. He was on his way to
Arlington Cemetery when he saw the plane
go over his car, hit some of the lamp
post, and then crashed into the
Pentagon. He abandons his car and spends
the majest of the day with the injured
and responders providing what comfort he
can to those around him. You can tell
which one is father because he has the
purple around his neck and he is the one
on his knees.
We're also going to talk about Staff
Sergeant Chris
Barman Balman. He was a cook and he had
retired from the military and at that
point he was a civilian at the Pentagon.
He along with Lieutenant
Colonel Paul Ted Anderson. They both
escaped the fire, but both of them made
the conscious decision to return back
into the Pentagon and search for
survivors. They managed to pull out
three people alive from the Pentagon.
Later that day, uh the sergeant is going
to work with the forensic team and
they're going to go into the Pentagon
numerous times and eventually they will
retrieve by the end of the day 63 marine
53 bodies from the Pentagon.
You will eventually receive a Purple
Heart for his injuries, a solders's
medal for his bravery and nightmares for
the rest of his life.
So, now we're going to talk about
Lieutenant Colonel Willis. At 9:37,
Colonel Willis is in a conference room
in the um uh I think she's in the D-ring
or the E-ring.
Um they're having a conference. They're
basically it's her turn to talk. she
starts talking and suddenly her entire
office the the conference room that
she's in catches on fire. Um so they
have managed to get out of the room and
what they do is they grab the ankle of
the person in front of them and then
they're crawling and they haven't
they're not familiar with the building.
They just move back in. They're not sure
which way is out, which way is up. All
they know is everything around them is
on fire. Everything is pitch black and
they are just trying to find a way out
and she's leading them. So she actually
manages to find a speck of light and she
goes towards the light and realize that
she has found a window.
What's the problem with the windows?
The problem with the windows is the
windows are now blast resistant windows.
You cannot break them. In fact, one of
the Marines who is with her picks up a
printer, throws it at the window, and it
literally bounces right back up at him.
And she's thinking to herself, "Oh my
god, I I I brought all of these people
to the Pentagon, to this exit, and we're
going to die right here in front of this
window." Until one of the personnel
realizes that the window is loose and
one So, the cocking that basically holds
the window in place is starting to peel
because of the heat. So people go in
with their fingernails and they're
pulling the cocking out of the window
and they finally get it loose enough
that they're able to push this huge
thick window out and it falls to the
ground and as a result of it falling to
the ground it catches the attention of
the people on the ground. So as a result
of this you have this massive group of
military who are now running towards
her. She's on the second floor and the
military who are there basically form a
human chain and the six people that she
is with crawl down this human chain and
end up getting taken away to triage
until the only two people still in that
window is herself and her colonel. And
she is screaming, "I have a way out. I
can I we can get out. I have a way out."
And she says, "We got to go back. If we
survived, somebody else survived. We
have to go back. We can't just leave."
And finally her lieutenant, her colonel
says,"I order you to go out of that
window." And so she does. She does and
her colonel follows her. Um she gets out
of the window and doesn't really really
remember anything else. Um she's out of
commission basically for 3 days. She
wakes up 3 days later in a burn unit in
Washington DC. Um she does survive the
day as did the six people that she
helped get out. They all survived. Um
she goes on to serve several tours I
believe in um Iraq.
Uh the Navy command center takes a
direct hit. So the Navy command center
is located on the western facade. I
honestly don't know where it is uh
exactly, but um you're you're you're a
captain of a naval vessel and you're at
port. You are sending order. You're
requesting new orders. You've seen
what's going on in New York. You don't
want to be a stationary target. A
stationary target, you know, it's much
easier to hit a moving target than it is
a stationary one. So, they're all
submitting requests for orders. Do I go
out to sea? Do I wait till the
refueling? I've got people at shore. Do
I go anyway? So, they're everybody, all
of these ships are submitting requests
for new orders. So you have all of these
fairly senior people who are rushing
their way to the Navy command center to
deal with all of these orders that are
coming in
and they take a direct hit. Um I don't
believe anyone got out. So out of uh
most of the p Navy personnel who are
killed at the Pentagon on 911, most of
them are in the Navy command center.
So, within minutes of the plane hitting
the Pentagon, firefighters are arriving
from all over Northern Virginia, DC.
They're from National Airport, from
Fairfax County, from Fort Meyers, you
name it. Everywhere in the region, they
are just showing up. You've got
ambulances, you've got metal, um you've
got helicopters that are just arriving
from everywhere. The military personnel
are going to rush to the impact zone and
the massive fire that has now engulfed
the western facade of the Pentagon
without gear. Many of them are going to
rush in to pull out the injured, the
dying, and the dead. At 10:10, the air
the Arlington County Fire Department has
now set up a command center. So, they
have established that they are now in
charge of this fire that is going on
behind them. And they are pulling aside
the military people and basically saying
that you're done. that um at this point
the military the structure is un
unstable and they can't go in anymore.
The problem is is if they go in and they
get injured then you have to send
firemen to go in and go get them. So
basically their idea was is that you
can't go in anymore. You now have to
leave this in the hands of the
firefighters who will go in to put out
the um the fire. And the military
personnel are all looking at each other.
They're looking at this announcement and
they all kind of have one thought
without ever saying it out loud, which
is, "Yeah, we don't care." Uh, they're
about to bumrush them. So, they're going
to bypass the the uh fired pirates, just
go around them and just keep going in
and out of the building as much as they
can until they really can't do it
anymore. And at the moment, they all
have this thought. They're all looking
at each other. Nobody's saying it out
loud. And they hear this huge crack, one
of the loudest sounds any of them have
ever heard. And what they are hearing is
at 10:10 the ceiling of the E-ring has
collapsed.
So to this day, nobody understands how
it held as long as it did. That fire was
anywhere between 1,600
and 2,000° F.
How that building and how that ceiling
held as long as it did,
the models, it doesn't make any sense,
but yet somehow it did. At that point,
the military realized that they really
can't keep going in and out of the
building anymore, that it's really time
to leave it to the firefighters, and
they concentrate on treating the injured
and allowing the firefighters to do
their jobs. So, all of this is going on.
The FBI has now arrived from the field
office. You have the National um
Transportation Safety Board. They have
arrived. You have all these federal
agencies that are arriving and they're
beginning their investigation into the
incident. But a new threat is now
emerging.
So you can see videos of this because
it's fascinating. So right around 10:20,
everybody's radio starts screaming. And
I do mean screaming. And everybody
starts screaming. The problem is is the
FAA has advised the military that there
is another flight that has been hijacked
and it is bound for Washington DC. Now
this suddenly makes some sense. You have
two planes hit the World Trade Center.
Two planes probably going to hit the
Pentagon.
So, we've been hit once. There's another
plane that has been hijacked. It is
heading to Washington DC. The assumption
is it is heading for the Pentagon.
So, there is a mandatory evacuation now
of the entire Pentagon building. So,
anyone who is staying is basically told
now they need to leave. So, you have the
fire, you know, the military personnel
are taking everybody. They're doing
triage. They're throwing them into
ambulances. Literally, you've got
ambulances that have four or five people
in it and they're just taking off and
they're trying to form this exterior
barrier getting everybody that they can
out of the Pentagon and as far away from
the Pentagon as they can because again
another plane is inbound.
So, but there's a problem. There is
something called the NMCC, which is the
National Military Command Center.
They're can't leave the Pentagon. At the
same time, they have a problem because
of water pressure. And you now have
smoke floating into the NMCC.
So, six Pentagon workers, these are not
military, these are people who are
employed to keep the Pentagon building
going. And they agree to stay behind
even though there's complete evacuation
and there's a plane that is inbound.
They have agreed to stay behind
because they're going to try to prevent
the ventil the smoke from getting into
the NMCC and restore water pressure. on
their radio. They hear quote, "Estimated
time of impact is 10 minutes." They know
the Pentagon. They know it better than
almost everybody else. They know there
is not enough time to get out.
So instead, they make their way to the
center courtyard of the Pentagon and
literally get on their knees. At the
same time, you've got four firefighters
from Fairfax County. They also have
heard the evacuation order, but now they
too know it's too late to get out.
They find the six Pentagon workers on
their knees and they literally go and
they join them and you know they hear
the estimated time of arrival and
they're on their knees and then suddenly
they hear the aircraft. They can
literally hear it. It is the loud one of
the loudest sounds you've ever heard.
You've got a plane that is coming at
you. It is supersonic and it is headed
right for them.
And here comes Penny.
So, Lieutenant Penny, Heather Penny,
along with her supervisor, uh, Colonel
Mark Sansville, they take off in their
X-16s from Andrews Air Force Base to
defend the capital from a hijacked US
aircraft. There's no time to arm the
planes and they take off anyway knowing
what they are being asked to do. Without
hesitation, they take off. um the way in
which uh Lieutenant Penny says it, she
gets on board the plane and Sansville
says, "I got the cockpit, which she
interprets to mean that she has the
tail."
Uh it's a very interesting story. They
were not part of NORAD. They were DC
National Guard. Um and basically the
Andrews Air Force Base got a call from
the White House operations center
basically saying get planes in the air.
So they are trying to get orders from
their Pentagon through their chain of
command because they can't take orders
from the White House. It's not the
president. It's somebody at the White
House operations center. So finally they
get orders. Yes, go ahead and take off.
By the time they get the orders, the
Pentagon has been hit and there's no
time to arm the aircraft and they just
take off.
Um, Lieutenant Penny does survive and
she ends up going on to serve two tours
in Iraq.
At 10:30 a.m. Rumsfeld is in the NMCC.
Rumsfeld is 78 years old. He is not
leaving the Pentagon. There has been a
continuation of op of a continuation of
uh operations which is a coupe plan. He
is basically ordered to go to an
alternate location. He's not going
anywhere. He basically sends his deputy
which is gentle by the name of Paul
Walzawitz. He sends him to the alternate
location. When asked later why he sent
his deputy, he says quote that is what
deputies are for.
1043 Rumsfeld raises the defcon from 5
to 3. The last time it was raised was
the 1973 during the Arab-Israeli war.
So by 10:40, the understanding is at
this point that that fourth plane has in
fact crashed
and they now have air cover in the form
of both Lieutenant Penny and Colonel
Sansville. And so they are going back at
10:40. they go back to resume um rescue
operations. Total of 106 people are
taken to area hospitals. 57 are treated
and released that day and 49 are
submitted for treatment. Most of those
who do end up with treatment are burn
victims. The area hospitals are able to
absorb the patients and it's not
necessary to transfer patients to
outside the immediate area. The Pentagon
never closes and it is never fully
evacuated. The first workers started
working at the Pentagon in February of
1942.
Operations have continued ever since.
So by 12:16, the last commercial
aircraft has now landed.
At 1:02 p.m., Rumsfeld is on the phone
with the president and he says, quotes,
"This is not a criminal action. This is
war. The Clinton administration treated
the terrorist attacks in 1993
um as criminal acts. The Bush
administration will treat 9/11 as war.
At 10 or sorry, 6:42, Romefeld holds a
press conference at the Pentagon and
announces, quote, "The Pentagon will be
in business tomorrow. Thousands of
Pentagon workers will show up the next
day for work in an office building which
is still burning."
Now, as you're hearing this these
numbers, things aren't making any sense
when you start thinking about it and
you're like, "Wait a minute. Okay, we
got 23,000 people who work at the
Pentagon at any given day and 125 were
killed.
This doesn't make sense." So, let's talk
about how that happened.
So this um image was created by the New
York or sorry by the LA Times and it
finally made sense to me once I saw this
image of exactly what happened. So you
had wedge one which was 5 days away from
being finished. So only about 800
workers had moved back into that
section. At the same time wedge two
which is this one over here was was
being basically cleared out. So most of
the people were not working in pen in
wedge 2 and most people were not working
in wedge one. So you hear stories of
survivors who went back into the
building and are running up and down the
hallways and nobody's answering them.
There's nobody there. It's not that
people have evacuated. It's literally
there was nobody there to begin with. It
was this very eerie feeling to see all
of these deaths and cubes and no people.
So people did go in and out of those
buildings several times trying to get
people out. Um but there weren't that
many people there to get out.
So due to the Pentagon being a
historical landmark, they could not
change the exterior of the building. So
when the Pentagon was built, the brick
wall was with uneven mortar behind it.
And brick cannot withstand an explosive
blast. So if the threat is TF bombs, we
need material that can withstand a
explosive blast. So as a result of this,
they basically take the brick out and
they replace it with steel beams
behind the limestone. So when the plane
comes in and hits limestone and steel,
the plane disappears in under a second.
The plane is gone. What continues is the
fireball.
So now you've got a fireball that's
going to go through the D-ring, the
sorry the E-ring, the D-ring, the C-
ring, and then hit the B- ring. I'll
show you a picture of that in a second.
So it is going to hit the steel. It will
disappear in under a second. There will
be nothing left of that aircraft. There
are a few things that exist, but not
much. Most of the aircraft disappears in
under a second. But all of that kinetic
energy is going to create the fireball.
You're also going to run into this
netting from the cavlar. You're going to
hit the windows and then you're going to
hit the fire sprinklers. Now, the
interesting thing if you look at this
picture is there are fire um
extinguishers in wedge one, but not in
wedge two.
So, the ones kind of on the exterior are
knocked out, but the ones further in
actually do turn on and start putting
out the fire. But in wedge 2, there are
no fire extinguishers. So, as a result,
it's going to burn out of control in
wedge 2.
So, again, you have this fireball and
the fireball is finally going to keep
going until eventually it's going to
create this perfect circle in the
B-ring. Now, people have seen pictures
of that and assumed somehow that this
means that it was a missile strike. It's
not a missile strike. It was the
fireball created from the energy of
basically an aircraft made of aluminum
hitting steel with 36,000 pounds of jet
fuel. That kinetic energy penetrated all
the way to the B-ring.
So let's talk about the Pentagon
memorial.
So the architects were Julie Beckman and
Keith Caseaseman. Their vision for the
memorial was selected from about 1,100
submissions. So Pentagon sets up
commission. They're going to build a
memorial. Uh it's mostly all military
people. They review some of the uh
submissions. About five or six of them
make their way up to the finalists. They
go through the finalists and this is the
one that won uh the commission to build
the memorial. The words describe its
purpose. We claim this ground in
memorance of the events of September
11th to honor the 184 people whose lives
were lost, their families and all those
whose sacrifice that we may live in
freedom we will never forget.
So what they did is they created these
benches. So there is one bench for one
all each 184 people and they did it
based upon age. So the youngest person
was Dana Faulenberger. She was three
years old. And the oldest one was John
um Kiki Yamiki. I I apologize. I
probably said his name wrong. And he was
71 years old. He was on board the
aircraft. So the benches that face uh
outwards were people inside the Pentagon
who were killed. And the benches that
face in were on board the aircraft when
it went down. Um if you go back to the
Pentagon um you know in the following
week or two, you'll see that these trees
that they planted are much bigger now.
And as a result, they have this memorial
looked looks very stark in this picture.
It's not stark anymore. It's it's much
more of a inviting and pleasant
atmosphere um because it creates this
canopy of trees over and I'm not a
nature person, but it it's a lovely
memorial.
So we have some more pictures of it. So
again, each bench represents an
individual. Now you can see here from
this picture kind of where the Pentagon
got hit. It's not a great one, but the
lighter the um the limestone, that is
where the Pentagon that's where the uh
where the plane went in. So if you see
the lighter, so over here is a little
bit darker and over here is a little bit
lighter. That is the newer section of
the Pentagon that was built after 911.
And here you see it at night. So at
night each one of these benches are
illuminated and then they have running
water underneath them which obviously
signifies life
and membrance.
And um we forget but the war fighters
who were in the Pentagon on that day the
following day went to war and had to
plan for war. And many of the people who
were in the Pentagon ended up in a war
zone. If not once, if not twice, some of
them three times. Some of them in
Afghanistan, some of them in But most of
the people who were milit members of the
military were going to spend some time
at some point in what they referred to
as the sandbox, which was either Iraq or
Afghanistan.
So, um, a lot of them have I I spoke to
a gentleman who came to one of my tours
and he was in the Pentagon on 911. He
was not one of the injured. was on in
another section and he said that he
never really dealt with 9/11. There was
no time. You know, right after 9/11 you
were planning to go to war and um you
had other responsibilities. So, he
really felt this gave my talk gave him
some closure um and the processing of
what happened to him and to his his
fellow workers who were in the Pentagon
on that day.
And uh here are my conclusions. Uh these
are my conclusions. You can agree with
them, you can disagree with them. These
are mine and mine alone. Um Khaled Shik
Muhammad's plan for the plains plan,
that's what he referred to it as, uh
were based on what he learned from the
failed Panka plot and from his relative
Ramsay Yousef. The events at Oklahoma
City and in Africa actually saved lives
at the Pentagon as it caused new
security measures, including the steel
and the blast resistant windows to be
put into place. And again, if that plane
had hit any other target, any other area
of the Pentagon,
it would have caused much more damage.
But it happened to hit the one section
of the Pentagon that had steel on the
exterior.
The renovation schedule meant uh for the
Pentagon meant that the offices in Wedge
one and wedge 2 would be mostly vacant
on September 11th, 2001.
The decision of the Bush administration
to teach these events as an act of war
continues to reverberate to this very
day. And tomorrow will be the 24th
anniversary of 9/11 and next year will
be 25 years. And it doesn't seem like it
was that long ago. I remember very
vividly where I was. Um before we kind
of get I'll tell you kind of my story.
Um does anyone have any questions?
Anything they want to put in the chat
room? Um anything that I talked about
you would like more information on
Uh, Robert, if you want to look at the
chat room and see if there's anything
perhaps I missed.
>> We'll do. Thank you.
>> Oh, the question is is what happened to
the 10 people who were in the middle?
They were all got out alive. So um
unlike in New York, there were no
injuries and no deaths from any of the
firemen who joined uh to put out the
blaze at um the Pentagon and the 11
people who were in the middle basically
they um exited the Pentagon and were not
injured on that day. Had some nightmares
but they were not injured as a result.
Very good question. Thank you.
Okay, so one of the other questions that
come in has to do with the daycare
center. There are a lot of stories about
that. I have not been able to confirm
most of them. Uh the daycare was was
located kind of I don't know Jason is
the right word attached but it was not
in the impact zone and I am not aware of
any children who were injured as a
result of the Pentagon being hit on 911.
And as Robert has just posted, you can
get um tours of the Pentagon. Um you
have to request them. I believe they're
only during the week. Um, so you kind of
have to submit the request. You submit,
you know, your um your date of birth and
that kind of stuff and then you can
schedule it. Um, they do them almost on
a daily basis, but again, they don't do
them on the weekends, so you would have
to take time off to do it. Um, there is
a three-year-old Dana Faulenberger. She
and her family were on board to
Faulberg, I think. I think I said that
wrong. Um, her entire family was on
board Flight 77. So, she was on board,
her sister was on board, and her parents
were on board.
Yes, there is a wonderful PBS
documentary on 911 in the Pentagon which
I highly recommend. Um, some of the
information that I got was as a result
of that documentary and they did
interview several of the Pentagon
workers and then the Fairfax fire u were
also interviewed as a result of that.
So, it is a very um it's a very
interesting story and I hope they do run
it tomorrow night. Um, it was very well
done.
I'm just trying to see if I'm missing
any other questions.
Um, and Robert has posted um some of my
additional YouTube programs. Um, I have
done several of them. Funny enough, my
most popular one is on Midway, which
kind of surprised me. I always assumed
though my most popular one would be on
on 911 at the Pentagon because there's
kind of aren't any lectures like this
available. So I assumed it would be on
that but no um I guess about 5,000
people have downloaded the um
presentation on Midway. The others some
of them are a thousand somewhere around
there. Um
>> and this program is being recorded. I'll
upload it to YouTube and email the link.
It's going to take me a day or two to do
that though.
>> Um, some of the other questions um has
been has the entire Pentagon been
reinforced now? The answer is yes. So,
the Pentagon renovations that began in
1998 were accelerated as a result of the
events of 9/11. And now the entire
exterior of the Pentagon or all of them
have those security measures which
include the Kevlar, the steel um beams
on the exterior um new um elevators have
been put in um additional steel and
obviously the fire extinguishers have
been fire sprinklers have been put in.
Uh one of the other questions is can
this happen again? I I human beings are
are incredibly um creative. Um I I don't
want to say I say it's much more
difficult now than it was on September
11th. Um it is more difficult for
terrorists to get into the country. It
is more difficult to use an aircraft as
a weapon. Um there are a lot of things
that are more difficult. Um but I will
never I can't ever say it could never
happen again. Um that is certainly our
intention. I work at TSA. Believe me, we
take that stuff very seriously. Um but
people are very creative and um what
happened on 911 took uh the military
planners and the national security
planners completely by surprise. Um it's
possible that somebody could come up
with something that daring um using
different technology at a different
time.
>> Hra, what about when you host your
in-person tours there? Is there
something in particular that um
surprises people the most or impresses
them the most? Any particular feedback
you get from people when they visit the
site?
Uh, I think a lot of people just didn't
know it was there. Um, you know, I I I
was talking to a woman who who came on
uh Sunday night and she was like, "I've
lived here for 20 years. I didn't even
know there was a 911 memorial."
>> Really? Wow.
>> So, yeah. So, it is a very um it's it's
it's very it's it's not as well visited
as a lot of the other because it's in
it's in Virginia and not in DC. So,
people don't it doesn't necessarily make
everybody's radar, but it's extremely
well done and I do really encourage
people to attend. I like going um or
arriving there right around 7:15, 7:10
um especially this time of year as the
sun sets because as the sun does set, it
does become a completely different
memorial. Um it just seems to get
quieter. Uh you can hear the water
running. Um you can see the lights come
on. It just becomes much more serene as
um kind of the twi as you get from
twilight to darkness. It just becomes a
different memorial. So I recommend
going, you know, just kind of as the sun
is setting so you can see it all in the
light and then see it as darkness um
imposes upon it. It it it does become a
very different memorial.
Um, yeah, somebody else said, "It
doesn't seem like it was 24 years ago."
It doesn't.
Um, yes, Zoe and uh Dana Faulenberg
um were the youngest on 911 and they
were on the aircraft with their family
and we had a lot of heroes on that day.
I'm sorry. I'm just going through some
of the comments. Uh, did the terrorists
have flight training on US soil? The
answer is yes. There were 19 hijackers.
Four of them were um very highly
educated and were and for example um uh
one of them was handpicked by Khaled
Shik Muhammad
um and they did flight training here in
the United States uh they did get
identification driver's licenses as a um
with paperwork that they had which is
one of the reasons why today we have to
go through that ring roll to get our
driver's licenses as a result of the
hijackers managing to get them. um they
were trained here in the United States
and um information was slowly making its
way to the FBI which was very odd about
a certain number of gentlemen who wanted
to learn how to fly but not land but um
that kind of stuff wasn't pieced
together until after 9/11 occurred.
Uh no, the entire Pentagon was not
evacuated. People were in that building
all night, trust me.
Um,
>> hey, here's all Dedra's other awesome
programs which are on our YouTube
channel and I sent the I posted the link
in the chat and I'll also email when I
email the recording that we're doing
tonight.
>> Yeah, I remember um somebody wrote about
being a kid in middle school when this
happened. Um, I was at uh I went into
the office the next day even on the so
on the 12th I was working at the
government. I had a job at the
Department of of Transportation on
Amtrak issues, believe it or not. And I
got a call from my boss and he's like
and I'm hysterical. I just I probably
should not have gone in, but I was in
the office and not doing much work, but
I was there. And um he's like, "You need
to do this." And I got all upset with
him and I said
something along the lines, "Do you know
that I still have family missing?"
Because at that point, I had a second
cousin who we weren't sure where they
were on that day. Turns out they were
already accounted for, just word hadn't
gotten back yet. And I remember saying,
"I still have family missing." And he
said, "Oh, I remember I you know what? I
remember Pearl Harbor." And I'm
thinking, "Yeah, but you weren't there.
You weren't in Pearl Harbor.
It's very different to actually be in
the city when it is under attack versus
being in Mississippi and there's an
attack on Hawaii.
It is slightly different. um slightly
different set of circumstances.
Um so the question is does planes still
fly over the Pentagon? They don't. It
just looks that way when you're in the
memorial. You see all these planes and
you're like, "God, they're flying right
over us." They don't. When the planes
take off from um from Reagan airport,
they're on a very very tight um flight
plan. They basically fly over the river.
Now the the difference between the river
and the Pentagon is you've ever been
there, it's not that far away from the
river, but they are very um limited as
to how far they can deviate from that
flight plan. Um it is very serious. They
have to take special training uh for
pilots to even land at Reagan airport
because there are just restrictions
about making sure they stay within a
very civic flight plan and that flight
plan takes them over the river and not
over either DC or the Pentagon.
Yeah, I read the 911 commission report
back toback. Um
there was just no, it just didn't occur
to people. I mean, my favorite is when
the when those planes took off um out of
Massachusetts
um because there was a hijacking, they
immediately went out to sea. Um the idea
was is what they had trained for is a
plane coming in from overseas that had
been hijacked. it just didn't occur to
the planners at the time that the plane
could actually generate out of, you
know, be a domestic aircraft. So, yeah,
it is it's hard when you look at it now,
you're like, well, of course, hindsight
is always 2020.
Um, see if I can see any of the other
comments.
Yeah, so people were in the city. I have
a lot of stories of people in New York
in my life and what they did.
Uh yeah, one of the things that somebody
talked about was the accident that
occurred last year. Was it this year?
This year? Um that was because you have
very congested airspace. So when you
think about where Reagan airport is and
the fact that the planes cannot fly over
DC and they cannot fly over the
Pentagon. So there's a very small window
area in which they can travel. So you
have the Coast Guard uh helicopters, you
have military helicopters, and then you
have military aircraft and then you also
have commercial aircraft and they all
have to stay within a very narrow and
also you've got the noise abatement.
Exactly. You have to have it in a very
narrow area of operations
and um that obviously was then one of
the factors as to what happened when
that plane crashed.
So, one of my friends said, "Great job,
Aunt DD."
Yeah.
So, anyone else have any questions? Or
Robert, do you have any comments as we
head towards 8:30?
>> Oh, um, no. Again, thanks so much for
doing this. If anyone's interested, um,
I have a video that shows pictures from
the Inerson tour that George has done. I
thought maybe I would cue that up just
so people could see what it looks like.
That's great. Why don't we do that?
>> That's a great idea. So, I need to stop
sharing. Hold on. Let me stop sharing. I
think if I can figure out how to do
that.
>> Um, well, maybe maybe I can't figure out
how to stop sharing.
>> Oh, it's okay. I can take care of
things. Oh, you can. Okay.
>> Yeah. Okay.
Did my screen pop up?
>> Not yet.
>> Oh.
Um,
>> see, I keep on getting this meeting is
being recorded button.
I can't seem to get behind that.